{
  "reference_number": "11544",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "Our Prime Minister, Jacinda Ardern, has called climate change \"my generation's nuclear free moment\". The Zero Carbon Act will be an\n absolutely essential framework for ensuring that New Zealand transitions to a low carbon economy and really meets its obligations\n under the 2013 Paris agreement. I strongly support the Zero Carbon Act"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "I support what is called the two basket approach to the issue how to deal with short lived and long lived greenhouse gases. It is\n imperative that we are guided by what science as to say about methane and other short lived gases. Science tells us that methane\n\n has much more impact than carbon dioxide in the short term, it warms the atmosphere at a greater rate. Therefore it is important that\n we stabilize short term gases first to reduce the the short term damage."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "New Zealand should not be using international carbon credits to off set local emissions. Using international carbon credits does not\n reduce our emissions at source at home. It does not force New Zealand businesses to seek low carbon ways of doing things and we\n\n know that using international carbon credits has done nothing to reduce NZ's carbon emissions, which have risen year on year. While\n I support the planting of new trees as carbon sinks, planting trees does not address the need to radically change our transport and\n\n energy systems that are currently too reliant on carbon emitting substances"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only in exceptional circumstances, or if it is determined that need to reduce our emissions at a faster rate"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "this is a very good idea because under the act, it will be the independent body, the Carbon Commission that will make the\n\n recommendations to the Govt."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Allowing an incoming govt to change the budgets will introduce too much uncertainty. This act is about making a radical change that\nthere is no going back from. Businesses and governments needs to commit fully to the future of a low carbon economy"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes I can see that there might be very very exceptional circumstances like a natural disaster that may require review of the second\n\nemissions budget"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "yes agree with the considerations. I want to call out particularly the importance of the governmentâ€™s obligations under the Treaty of\nWaitangi and the need for the goverment to work in partnership with iwi"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There must be clear and strict time frames to make Government produce the actual policy plans to achieve the emissions budgets.\n\nSix months is an adequate time period"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government needs to be guided by the following points: 1. Put the Treaty of Waitangi at the centre of this act 2. The principle of\nfairness is also critical. As we transition to a low carbon future, the goverment needs to take particular care of vulnerable communities\n\n(eg taranaki) and workers who may lose their livelihoods. Retraining and support needs to be available. 3. Care needs to be taken to\nensure that us baby boomers do not simply pass on the costs of meeting the emissions budgets onto younger generations 4. The\n\nGovernment also needs to consider wider environmental sustainability ( things like clean rivers) when making the plans to meet the\nemissions budgets The Government needs to be guided by the following points: 1. Put the Treaty of Waitangi at the centre of this act\n\nin order so the government needs to work closely with Iwi. 2. The principle of fairness is also critical. As we transition to a low carbon\nfuture, the goverment needs to take particular care of vulnerable communities (eg Taranaki) and workers / farmers who may lose their\nlivelihoods. Retraining and support needs to be available. 3. Care needs to be taken to ensure that us baby boomers do not simply\n\npass on the costs of meeting the emissions budgets onto younger generation. 4. The Government also needs to consider wider\nenvironmental sustainability ( things like clean rivers) when making the plans to meet the emissions budgets"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes most definitely. An independent Climate change commission is absolutely key to meeting our carbon emissions targets so that is\n\ncan provide expert advice and play a role in holding the government to account. The CCC should not be the one to make the\ndecisions about emission budgets, it is the role of the democratically elected government to take responsibility for these hard calls\n\nand be accountable to the people"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "as I said above The CCC should not be the one to make the decisions about emission budgets, it is the role of the democratically\nelected government to take responsibility for these hard calls be accountable to the people"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes I agree with the list. However I would like to point out the Public Health expertise is not listed and should be included"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Climate change is here now, we are already experiencing extreme weather events more frequently. Drought and flooding are more\ncommon and sea levels will continue to rise in the short as well as longer term"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes agree with these functions Yes the government must prepare a national climate risk assessment and develop policies to\n\nremediate the risks. Local councils will need to be involved to address local specifics., Monitoring and reporting is absolutely essential\nalso."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes this is a very good idea. Transparency will prevent organisation's green washing"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "thank you for the opportunity to make a submission. The UK's Zero carbon act has been very effective in enabling the long term\nplanning that is required to transition to a low carbon economy. I wholeheartedly believe that this Act is New Zealand's last and best\n\nhope to reach the goal of net long term carbon emissions by 2040."
    }
  ]
}
